Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books
1742-2014
RBD2
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Rare Book Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
21 linear feet 15 boxes
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections
Collection of ephemera relating to the marketing of books, consisting of prospectuses, adverts, catalogs, etc.
Collection of ephemera relating to the marketing of books, consisting of prospectuses, adverts, catalogs, etc.
This collection was purchased as a dealer lot. It does not represent a private collector's purposeful collecting strategy.
Open for research.
Purchase, 2014.
Publishers and publishing; Ephemera; Publisher's advertisements; Publisher's catalogs; Publishing history
- Publishing Ephemera Dated Before 1800, 1742-1799; 4 boxes (2 partial)
  This series contains pamphlets dated before 1800.
  Arrangement follows the order of the original Excel inventory.
  - Compaing, Monsig.: Agli illustriss. e reverendiss. Monsignori vescovi d'Italia [heading title], 1782; 42384; portion of 1 box
    Author: Compaing, Monsig.
    Venezia: Pietro Valvasense.
    Broadside (210 mm.); uncut, fine. Prospectus announcing the publication of "l'Opera della Santità, e de'Doveri de'Sacerdoti".
  - Grose, Francis: The antiquities of England and Wales: being a collection of views of the most remarkable ruins and antient buildings, accurately drawn on the spot. To each view is added, an historical account of its situation, when and by whom built, with every interesting circumstance relating thereto; collected from the best authorities, 1772; 41255; portion of 1 box
    Author: Grose, Francis
    London: S. Hooper
    Folio, unpaged; 6 engraved half-page illustrations; self wrappers, edges a bit toned and spotted, faint stain at bottom right-hand corner of upper cover, else very good. Prospectus for a 6 volume work (1772-1787), in which are reproduced specimen illustrations from Canterbury, Ipswich, Odiam, Colchester, and Southampton, with detailed descriptions. The whole printed on exceptionally thick paper. Penn State and Toronto only of the prospectus in OCLC.
  - King, Edward: Vestiges of Oxford Castle., 1796; 36303; portion of 1 box
    Author: King, Edward
    London: W. Bulmer & Co.
    4to; pp. iv, 30; 5 plates from the work (pls. CXXVI-CXXX); prospectus for a piece described as "a small fragment of a work, intended to be published speedily; on the history of antient castles; and on the progress of architecture". Green boards, edges and corners worn, pages untrimmed.
  - Alexander, William: Costume of China. Speedily will be published. Sketches from nature, made in China, in the year 1793, 1797; 40747; portion of 1 box
    Author: Alexander, William
    London: G. Nicol.
    Broadside, folio (321 mm.); a few shallow tears along left-hand edge, evidence of having been previously tipped-in on right margin; a very good copy. Prospectus for the rare first edition, issued in four parts, 1797-1799, containing 48 colored engravings by Alexander, the junior draftsman on the Macartney Embassy to China. Full page contemporary manuscript "Curious Predictions 2" on verso, entirely about the predicted fall of Napoleon. This prospectus unrecorded.
  - Bickham, George: Proposals for printing by subscription the Universal penman, 1742; 42494; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bickham, George
    London: Bickham, George.
    Broadside (408 x 246 mm.); moderate foxing and soiling, hinged to mat; very good. Scarce Broadside for "the most curious book of its kind hitherto extant," soliciting subscribers for the second (and first complete) issue in parts of Bickham's magnum opus, the outstanding English writing manual of the 18th-century, following the 1733-1741 serial first issue also published by subscription. According to Muir, the Bickham venture was "the first recorded attempt to issue in periodical parts a work that was intended for subsequent issue in book form" (P.H. Muir, "The Bickhams and their Universal Penman," The Library, series 4, Volume 25, pages 162, 165, and 185).
    Filed under Bick.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1800s, 1800-1899; portions of 4 boxes
  This series contains pamphlets dated after 1800 and before 1900.
  - Payne, John Howard: Jam jehan nima., 1833; 36262; 1 item
    Author: Payne, John Howard
    New York: John Howard Payne
    8vo, pp. 8; "prospectus of...a weekly periodical upon a plan never before attempted". Text in two columns. Previous folds, edges and corners worn, tear to last leaf through middle of last paragraph, text still legible. Back leaf provides List of subscribers. With TLS from the author to Webb, Esq., written "in the hope of adding to my number of subscribers".
    Missing as of 9/9/2014
  - Eastman, Edwin: Seven and nine years among the Camanches (sic) and Apaches, 1873; 36245; 1 item
    Author: Eastman, Edwin
    Jersey City, N.J.: Clark Johnson
    8vo, pp. 8; wood-engraving portraits and illustrations throughout, text in two columns, first describing Eastman's supposed kidnapping before giving over to the advertising of a magical panacea discovered by Eastman during his time with the Indians. The work is described by G.P. Garrison as "a revolting fictitious story written to advertise Dr. Clark Johnson's Indian blood syrup."
  - Collectio classicorum latinorum, 1820; 42370; 1 item
    Stamperia del Seminario di Padova.
    Broadside (189 mm.); contemporary owner's unobtrusive ink marks, else near fine. Publisher's list of titles from the series, which include the works of Julius Caesar, Catullus, and Cicero, among many others.
  - Frazer, Alexander: A key to the prophecies of the Old and New Testaments, which are not yet accomplished...First American edition, 1802; 38112; portion of 1 box
    Author: Frazer, Alexander
    Philadelphia: David Hogan
    Broadside, 4to (263 mm.); toned, edges trimmed, very good. Prospectus from the Philadelphia Repository, Extra, for Saturday, November 13, 1802; provides the work's table of contents. Postscript to the Extra printed on verso, along with a small advertisement for James Carson's "A Practical Grammar of the English Language" and a proposal for a collection of sacred music.
  - Carey, Mathew: Bible, 1803; 36435; portion of 1 box
    Author: Carey, Mathew
    Philadelphia: Mathew Carey
    Bifolium, 4to, text only on front cover; printed letter dated August 18, 1803, "Sir, I take the liberty to send you herewith a specimen of the paper, printing, and engravings of my standing Edition of the Bible". Integral letter addressed to Mr. W.W. Woodward, red wax seal; top third cleanly separated from the bottom due to previous folds. This Mathew Carey prospectus not in OCLC.
  - [Dennie, Joseph]: The port folio, a monthly miscellany, dedicated, in cheif, to original communications in the popular departments of science combined with occasional criticism, clasical disquisitions, miscellaneous essays, records of the progress of the fine and useful arts, with all the extensive and variegated departments of polite literature, merriment and wit. Conduted by Oliver Oldschool, Esq., 1809; 36263; portion of 1 box
    Author: [Dennie, Joseph]
    Philadelphia: Bradford and Inskeep
    8vo, pp. 11; prospectus for Dennie's periodical, either written wholly or in part by him. Soiling, tear to front leaf not affecting text, edges and corners worn and chipped. BAL 4640.
  - Trommsdorff, Bartolomeo: La callopistria ossia la chimica diretta al bello del mondo elegante...Traduzione dal tedesco con aggiunte del dottor Giovanni Pozzi, 1815; 42364; portion of 1 box
    Author: Trommsdorff, Bartolomeo
    Milano: Giovanni Silvestri.
    Broadside (164 x 108 mm.); mostly fine. Prospectus for the "edizione secunda notabilmente aumentata".
  - Arrigo da Settimello: Arrighetto ovvero trattato contro all'avversità della fortuna...Edizione eseguita sul teste del 1730, 1815; 42365; portion of 1 box
    Author: Arrigo da Settimello
    Broadside (170 x 104 mm.); fine. Sample title pages of this and the publisher's "Saggio Poetico ossia le tre guerre puniche in ottava rima".
  - Vico, Giambattista: Principj di scienza nuova...d'intorno alla comune natura delle nazioni colla vita dell'autore, 1816; 42362; portion of 1 box
    Author: Vico, Giambattista
    Milano: Tipografia di Giovanni Silvestri.
    Bifolium, small 8vo; edges a bit worn, else very good. Prospectus for the sixth edition with additional advertisements for Scheidlein's "Analisi della Processura Civile Austriaca ovvero Schiarimenti sul Regolamento Giudiziario Civile" and Giuseppe Marocco's "Della Necessita di un Difensore nelle Cause Criminali qualunque sia la Processura Penale".
  - Chesterfield, Lord: Avvertimenti di Lord Chesterfield a suo figlio intorno agli uomini ed ai costumi, ossia nuovo sistema d'educazione, 1816; 42363; portion of 1 box
    Author: Chesterfield, Lord
    Broadside (167 x 99 mm.); near fine. Prospectus for an Italian translation of Chesterfield's Letters to His Son on the Art of Becoming a Man of the World and a Gentleman.
  - Nares, Robert: Illustrations of difficult words and phrases occurring in the English writers of the age of Elizabeth., 1818; 36425; portion of 1 box
    Author: Nares, Robert
    London: Bensley and Son
    4to, unpaginated; grey printed wrappers in which is bound a sample section of the dictionary (BAR-BED), the leaves of which have been trimmed to size, affecting text; back leaf advertising the publication of six other titles from the same press. Contemporary autograph note to back cover.
  - The American practical, moral and religious catechism, to which is annexed a variety of easy and interesting reading lessons, for young scholars, tending to promote sentiments of morality and virtue., 1821; 36287; portion of 1 box
    New York
    Broadside, 4to (320 mm.). Proposal "for the printing by subscription" of this work, which does not appear to have made it to print. Manuscript list of subscribers bottom 2/3 of leaf. Previous folds, ink stains to Broadside verso, name of compiler and original price have been crossed out, small circular loss where the price has been marked out. A rare, unrecorded prospectus.
  - Johnson, John: Typographia; or, the printers' instructor, 1822; 41975; portion of 1 box
    Author: Johnson, John
    London: Apollo Press.
    Bifolium, 8vo; toning, chips and tears along edges, much of spine perished, else good. 3 reduced specimen pages from the octavo, twelves, and eighteens editions provided. Prospectus advertises the 2-volume work as "in the Press, And will appear in the ensuing Spring," although the first edition does not seem to have appeared until 1824. Prospectus not in OCLC.
  - Hornor, Thomas: Prospectus. View of London, and the surrounding country, taken with mathematical accuracy from an observatory purposely errected over the cross of St. Paul's Cathedral, 1823; 43206; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hornor, Thomas
    London: Hornor, T.
    Second edition, 8vo, pp. 31; folding engraved frontispiece, 1 lithographic folding plate, and 2 additional multifolding plates; original pictorial wrappers, respined, edges worn with small losses to corners; some interior foxing, else very good and sound. Thomas Hornor, a talented perspective draughtsman, obtained permission to build a shack on the scaffolding erected on St. Paul's for replacing the ball and cross above the Cathedral's dome. On it Hornor proposed to draw a huge panorama of London, which this Prospectus offers to the public in the form of four engravings. This was to be supplemented by a Select View in London and its Neighbourhood, a work of one hundred engravings available in ten fascicles. Neither project was ever completed, making the prospectus itself the only printed result of Hornor's work.
  - Redouté, Pierre Joseph.: Les roses par P. J. Redouté, peintre de fleurs ... avec le texte par C. A. Thorry ... edition in-octavo quarante livraisons in-8°, de quatre plances coloriées chacune, au prix de 3 fr. 50 cent. Prospectus... [cover title], 1824; 42455; portion of 1 box
    Author: Redouté, Pierre Joseph.
    Paris: Panckoucke, C. L. F.
    8vo, pp. 4; engraved printed color plate of the Rosa centifolia; original brown printed wrappers; stitched,as issued; fine. The publisher's original prospectus for the octavo edition of Redouté's Les Roses, published in 3 volumes 1824-26. Includes 3 pages of text outlining the scope of the work, and details on ordering and the schedule of publication is outlined on the back wrapper. See Sitwell, Great Flower Books, p. 128.
  - Manifesto d'associazione [heading title], 1829; 42381; portion of 1 box
    Torino: Marzorati, Vercellotti, e Comp.
    Bifolium, 4to; previous fold, else near fine. Prospectus for the Biblioteca Economica, religious works, and others.
  - Associazione allo specchio geografico, 1831; 42373; portion of 1 box
    Roma: Presso Giunchi.
    8vo, unpaged; original self wrappers, top edge a bit darkened, minor wear from handling, else near fine. Order form laid in.
    Filed under P.
  - Vallardi, Giuseppe: Manuale calcografico per l'artista, il mercante e l'amatore, 1832; 42374; portion of 1 box
    Author: Vallardi, Giuseppe
    Milano: Pietro e Giuseppe Vallardi.
    8vo, pp. xvi; self wrappers; some spotting along top edge, else fine. Contains an important programmatic manifesto followed by the description of the new work with prices.
    Filed under V.
  - Torrey, Jesse, Jr.: The national library, advocate of civil and religious liberty; or Universal repository of useful knowledge. Vol. I, no. 1. May 15, 1833, 43068; portion of 1 box
    Author: Torrey, Jesse, Jr.
    Philadelphia: Sleeper, J.R.
    8vo, pp. 16; stitched self-wrappers, untrimmed; edges darkened and a bit foxed; over all very good. "The National Library is intended to be a domestic repository or cyclopaedia of essential information, moral, civil, physiological, medical, mechanical, agricultural, scientific, and miscellaneous." This introductory pamphlet is a prospectus demonstrating that the Library and Advocate will be "an independent, impartial messenger of intelligence." The maiden issue present articles on the Washington Reformation, Nullification, paper money and banking, Medical Reformation, and inter alia, "An Essay on Native Depravity," by "A Friend to Mankind". Not in American Imprints or Sabin.
  - Missel selong les différens rites de l'église catholique, 1840; 42375; portion of 1 box
    Paris: François Pastori et Comp.
    8vo, pp. 6, [1]; steel-engraved vignette, full-page illustration on p. [7]; unbound self wrappers; small loss to bottom right-hand corner not affecting text, else very good. Subscription bulletin laid in.
  - [Miss Leslie's magazine], 1843; 38062; portion of 1 box
    Philadelphia: Miss Leslie's Magazine
    Broadside, large 8vo (262 mm.); color decorative boarder of birds, butterflies, and flowers; stains and foxing, minor tear to bottom left hand edge not affecting text. Heading reads "To the Ladies," dated 1st. March, 1843, and is signed by F. Quarre. Although the piece does not mention the name of the journal, the dates and contents suggest that it is an advertisement for Miss Leslie's Magazine, which ran from January to December, 1843.
  - Yes: The congressional globe and appendix, 1843; 38067; portion of 1 box
    Author: Yes
    Washington City: Blair & Rives
    Broadside, folio (340 mm.); stains, small tear to top edge and loss between heading and text, not affecting text; printed in two columns. Prospectus for this Washington-based newspaper "made up of the daily proceedings of the two Houses of Congress...The Appendix is made up of the President's annual message, the reports of the principal officers of the Government that accompany it, and all the long speeches of members of Congress." Blank space at bottom in which to list the subscribers' names. OCLC locates one copy of this prospectus, at the New York Historical Society.
  - Seyfred, J.F.: Anglo-Romaic reader: Or guide to a practical knowledge of the modern Greek language. Containing new and plain rules on pronunciation; the parts of speech exemplified; familiar and elementary phrases; dialogues; select pieces in prose and verse, &c. The whole with a literal translation into English., 1845; 36255; portion of 1 box
    Author: Seyfred, J.F.
    New York: J.F. Trow & Co.
    Bifolium, 4to, prospectus with integral address leaf with 1 1/2 p. autograph letter signed by Henry Bernhard addressed to J.A. Kerly of East Hampton, Long Island. Address panel, postal hand stamps, red wax seal. Previous folds, minor foxing, some toning on address leaf, small circular loss at tail of address leaf at seal, but not affecting manuscript.
    Filed under T.
  - Neale, Wm. L.: True American, 1845; 45459; portion of 1 box
    Author: Neale, Wm. L.
    Lexington, Kentucky: True American
    Broadside printed receipt (approx. 5.1 x 15.9 cm) accomplished in manuscript; typographical decoration along left-hand edge; fine. Receipt from the office of the anti-slavery newspaper The True American, which ran in 1845 and 1846, made out to the publisher George Merriam. Dated June 8, 1845, just a few days after the first appearance of this publication, on the 3rd. Merriam paid $2.50 for a year's subscription. Signed by Wm. L. Lane. The paper was published weekly by Cassius Marcellus Clay (cousin of Henry Clay).
  - Worcester magazine and historical journal., 1845; 36258; portion of 1 box
    Worcester, Mass.: William Lincoln and Chris C. Baldwin
    Broadside, 4to (247 mm.) prospectus for the publication of a new periodical, of which, we are told, "No work of the same size and style of execution has been offered at a price so moderate as this". Verso side provides conditions and order form. Small tears from previous folds not affection text.
  - The national intelligencer., 1849; 36259; portion of 1 box
    Washington, D.C.: Gales & Seaton
    Single sheet folded into 4 leaf pamphlet, pages uncut, 4to; prospectus with integral address leaf. Address panel "To the postmaster at Lyme, N.H.", postal stamps. Previous folds.
  - The Union Democrat., 1851; 36298; portion of 1 box
    Manchester, N.H.: W.H. Gilmore & Co.
    Broadside, long 4to (353 mm.); "Prospectus for a Democratic paper at the City of Manchester...To the Democrats of the County of Hillsborough and the patrons of the Manchester Democrat in particular." Bottom half provides room as an order order form.
    Filed under W.
  - Webster, Daniel.: Proposals for publishing by subscription a new and uniform edition of the speeches, forensic arguments, and diplomatic papers of..., 1851; 44664; portion of 1 box
    Author: Webster, Daniel.
    Boston: Little and Brown i.e. Little, Brown
    4to, bifolium printed on blue paper; text printed on p. [1] only; previous folds, small loss from wax seal damage not affecting text, else very good. Announcement of a new annotated edition of the minor works of Webster to be published in six volumes, including 200 copies to be printed on large paper. Manuscript lettered signed "Little & Brown" addressed to Messrs. G and C. Merriam regarding an order of 10 copies of two titles (Chitty's Pleadings (?), in 3 volumes, and one other).
  - New books and new editions published by Ticknor, Reed, and Fields, 1851; 37555; portion of 1 box
    Boston: Ticknor, Reed, and Fields
    Bifolium, 12mo; list of publications includes Henry W. Longfellow's writings; Nathaniel Hawthorne's writings; and Goethe's "Wilhelm Meister" and "Faust". Disbound.
  - Pitts, F.E.: Zion's harp, 1852; 43896; portion of 1 box
    Author: Pitts, F.E.
    Louisville: Stevenson, E.
    New edition, "very much enlarged, and otherwise improved," bifolium, 4to; previous folds, contemporary hand has cancelled the drop title "Will be ready about the first of June, 1852," and replaced it in manuscript with "is now ready & out"; minor ink spots and soiling, else very good and sound. Advertisement for three religious works, the first being a collection of hymns; the latter two titles are "Sermons for the College, being a collection of original sermons, contributed by distinguished ministers of different Protestant denominations in the United States together with two sermons by eminent living ministers of England: to which is added a supplementary essay by Rev. Thos. F. Akers," third edition; and "Lights of Temperance. A new work," edited by James Young, third edition.
  - Baldwin, Jo. G.: Party leaders, 1854; 43914; portion of 1 box
    Author: Baldwin, Jo. G.
    New York: D. Appleton & Company.
    Bifolium, 4to; printed on pale grey paper, text on p. [1] only; previous folds, small tear affecting the "P" in "Party," else very good and sound. Autograph note signed on p. [3]; integral envelope, wax seal intact. Advertisement circular for Baldwin's collection of "politico-biographical sketches of Thomas Jefferson, Alexander Hamilton, Henry Clay, Andrew Jackson, and John Randolph of Roanoke".
  - Cooper, J. Fenimore: A new and improved edition of the entire works...with all his latest corrections and revisions; entitled the people's edition. With an elaborate life of the author, 1854; 39284; portion of 1 box
    Author: Cooper, J. Fenimore
    New York: Stringer & Townsend.
    Broadside, large 4to (277 mm.); a bit toned along previous folds, shallow tears not affecting text; a good copy. Prospectus for this one-volume edition of Fenimore's works, announced 3 years arter his death. Includes a "blurb" by Victor Hugo, "the greatest of contemporary romanticists and critics, declares that Cooper is a creator indeed 'a prodigious genius'".
  - Cecchetti, Bartolomeo: Programma di un'opera generale sull'arte vetraria, 1861; 42377; portion of 1 box
    Author: Cecchetti, Bartolomeo
    Venezia: Tipografia del Commercio.
    8vo, pp. 18, [1]; pictorial grey wrappers (soiling), edges toned and spotted, some wear from handling; rubber stamp "Biblioteca Malfèr" inside front wrapper, else interior fine.
  - The laws of Nevada territory, 1862; 42355; portion of 1 box
    San Francisco: Kenny & Alexander.
    Broadside (210 x 132 mm.); printed on blue paper; previous folds, small embossed stamp, Kent Mills Commercial; near fine. The earliest publishing prospectus for the Nevada Territory, here issued just after Nevada was organized as a territory and, auspiciously, advertising the impending publication of its first session laws: "Containing the Organic Act creating the Territory; a full List of all the Federal and Territorial Officers; also, the names of Members and Officers of the Legislative Assembly".
  - The fire lands' pioneer. Enlarged edition, 1864; 44706; portion of 1 box
    Norwalk, OH: Fire Lands' Historical Society.
    Bifolium, 4to; text printed on p. [1] only; previous folds, else about fine. With an autograph letter signed by the secretary of the Society Committee's D.H. Pease, asking Henry White, Esq., of New Haven, "to...call the attention of those friends in the 'Mother' State who feel an interest in the history of the 'Fire Lands'". Prospectus for a fifth volume of the Fire Lands' Historical Society Pioneer. Canvassing agent's integral order blank printed at bottom of p. [1].
  - The phrenological journal and life illustrated., 1871; 36260; portion of 1 box
    New York: S.R. Wells